"Can You Reverse Type 2 Diabetes
with a Whole Food, Plant-Based Diet?"
The goal of lifestyle treatment
for type 2 diabetes
is to reverse it,
drive it into remission,
meaning normal blood sugars
on a normal diet without drugs,
and exactly that
can be achieved optimally
with a whole food,
plant-based diet,
as I’ve reviewed before.
For individuals
who have had type 2 diabetes
for more than eight years,
often having faced
multiple complications,
remission may be
harder to achieve
because a significant number
of insulin-producing beta cells
in their pancreas
are already depleted.
Even though full remission
may not be possible
for all patients,
most everyone may still be able
to find their way
towards better health
and improve blood sugar control
without adding
more medications
and could even reduce
the medications
they are already on.
You’ve heard
of prescribing meds,
but what about
deprescribing them?
Deprescribing medications among
patients with type 2 diabetes
is actually something
that’s more common
in lifestyle medicine
because intensive,
therapeutic lifestyle change
works pretty effectively
and can result
in substantial and rapid drops
in blood glucose.
In order to avoid blood glucose
dropping too low,
which results in hypoglycemia,
medications need to be adjusted.
And the potential benefits
of deprescribing meds
in older individuals
is extensive,
including reduced harm from
taking many drugs at one time.
It not only reduces risk
of adverse drug reactions
and lowers medication costs,
but it actually improves
people’s ability
to take the drugs
they need to be taking
because they aren’t overwhelmed
with managing so many.
Deprescribing medications is
individualized to each patient,
but, generally,
most medical practitioners
will first target the meds
most likely to cause
dangerously low blood sugars,
such as sulfonylurea drugs
like Glucotrol or Micronase,
and insulin.
When lifestyle medicine
practitioners were surveyed,
their perceived negative effects
were minimal,
with things like "pushback
from insurance companies"
or patients upset
they hadn’t been told earlier
about the efficacy
of a plant-based diet
and that less medication
is possible.
I’d be angry too!
The list of perceived positive
effects is full of statements
like "improved patient morale,"
"empowering to patients,"
and "improved sense
of well-being and hope."
Check out this randomized
controlled trial
of a whole food, plant-based
intensive
lifestyle intervention
among people
with type 2 diabetes.
Successfully improving
blood glucose measures
while also reducing medications,
compared to
standard medical care.
More than half of those
in the plant-based diet
and exercise group
reduced their
diabetes medications
compared with only a fifth
of those on the standard care.
And this was also true for
their heart disease medications.
Double win.
And contrary to
what some may think,
weight loss
wasn’t necessarily required
to result in remission.
Just the plant foods
and exercise
were so powerful together,
supporting what we already know:
food can indeed be medicine.
What about
those other health concerns
that come along with diabetes,
such as increased risk
of cardiovascular disease?
A systematic review
and meta-analysis
of randomized controlled trials
found plant-based
dietary patterns
result in significantly better
glucose control
and lower
LDL cholesterol levels,
one of the big risk factors
for heart attacks.
People also lost weight
and decreased
their waist circumference,
which serves as a sort of proxy
for excess visceral fat,
a kind of fat that can be
particularly detrimental
to health.
Type 2 diabetes
is considered
one of the most psychologically
demanding chronic conditions.
Just think about all that people
with diabetes have to manage,
medications,
doctors’ appointments,
and regularly stabbing
their finger
to get blood sugar readings,
not to mention the fears
of going blind,
going on dialysis,
and getting parts
of their lower limbs amputated.
A systematic review
of the effectiveness
of plant-based diets
on well-being found that,
compared to standard care,
plant-based diets are associated
with significant improvements
in emotional well-being,
depression, and quality of life,
along with overall improvements
in health.
As the incidence and prevalence
of diabetes continues to rise,
the time is now
for clinicians to recommend
a low-fat, whole food,
plant-based diet
to all of their patients,
but especially those patients
living with and at risk
for type 2 diabetes.
Whole food, plant-based diets
can prevent diabetes,
as well as change
the course of the disease,
by controlling blood sugar
naturally
with no known
negative side effects.